<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the anniversary meeting of the Sons of clergy-men, in the church of St. Mary-le-Bow, December 4, 1684 by Francis Lord Bishop of Ely, and president of the society.</title>
            <author>Turner, Francis, 1638?-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63885</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3286</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3975</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12186921</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12186921</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55807</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63885)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55807)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 880:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the anniversary meeting of the Sons of clergy-men, in the church of St. Mary-le-Bow, December 4, 1684 by Francis Lord Bishop of Ely, and president of the society.</title>
                  <author>Turner, Francis, 1638?-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Playford, for Henry Bonwick ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Genesis XVIII, 19 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55807:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55807:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the <hi>Anniverſary Meeting</hi> Of the SONS of CLERGY-MEN, In the Church of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Mary-le-Bow, <hi>DECEMBER</hi> 4, 1684.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> FRANCIS <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> ELY, <hi>and</hi> PRESIDENT <hi>of the</hi> Society.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Playford,</hi> for <hi>Henry Bonwick</hi> at the <hi>Red Lyon</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:55807:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55807:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful the STEWARDS Of the late ANNIVERSARY MEETING OF <hi>Clergy-Men's Sons,</hi> And the reſt of the <hi>Governours of the Charity for Relief of the poor Widows and Children of Clergy-Men.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My moſt Honoured Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THough I could heartily wiſh you had been pleaſed to reſerve for ſome better occaſion the juſt power you have with me, and that you had demanded ſome other proofs of the due regard I muſt have to all your motions, inſtead of obliging me to publiſh this very plain diſcourſe, yet I ſhould not make you a ſuitable return for all the Honour you have done me, ſhould I obſtinately refuſe whatever you earneſtly requeſt; but whatever credit I may loſe (if I have any to loſe) I ſhall not think I have loſt my labour, if I can perſwade <hi>my Brethren of the Houſe of Levi,</hi> to take ſpecial care that this <hi>Charity begin at home,</hi> this great <hi>Charity</hi> of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:55807:3"/> 
               <hi>Education.</hi> The beſt portion that any Parents can leave their Children, the only conſiderable Portion that many of the beſt <hi>Clergy-men</hi> can leave theirs; and one of the beſt Legacies they can leave this Corporation will be ſuch well bred Children, as will deſerve that Character St. <hi>Paul</hi> beſtows on <hi>Timothy, Who will naturally care for your ſtate.</hi> For to make <hi>our Children</hi> as perfectly good Chriſtians as they ought to be, will be the moſt effectual means to tye them faſt to the Intereſts of this Body; the ſtiff abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the good Old Cauſe in <hi>Scotland,</hi> have ignorance and impudence enough to <hi>Chriſten their Children into the</hi> ſolemn League <hi>and</hi> Covenant (as if that were the Covenant of Grace, and ſo do ſome of them call it.) Let us ſhow as much <hi>zeal</hi> and more <hi>according to knowlege,</hi> by bringing <hi>our Youth</hi> to <hi>keep their Baptiſmal Vow,</hi> and then they will never fail to Honour and Love the <hi>Church</hi> in which they were <hi>Born</hi> and <hi>Baptiz'd.</hi> But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, Let all the Sons of Church-men be ſo well Tutor'd and Taught, that they may be ſecur'd and ſettled in this reſolution, to live and dy true Sons of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>As I am one of the meaneſt of thoſe Sons, ſo I am My moſt Honoured Friends, Your moſt faithfull and moſt humble Servant, <hi>Fran. Ely.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55807:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the SONS OF THE CLERGY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>GENESIS XVIII. <hi>v.</hi> 19.</bibl>
               <q>For I know him, that he will Command his Children and his Houſhold after him, and they ſhall keep the way of the Lord, to do juſtice and judgment; that the Lord may bring upon Abraham that which he hath ſpoken of him.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe words are part of a great and worthy Character which God was pleaſed to give of <hi>Abraham, the Father</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:55807:4"/> 
               <hi>of the Faithful;</hi> who at his Hoſpitable Gate had newly entertain'd three Sacred Gueſts, whom though the Patriarch at firſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended to be but Men, yet we may juſtly ſuppoſe they were more than Angels, for ſince one of them is all along ſtyled <hi>the Lord,</hi> and ſince <hi>Abraham</hi> makes Addreſſes of Adoration and Prayer directly to him: Unleſs we could allow the <hi>Socinian</hi> Doctrine, <hi>That it were Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to Worſhip a (reature,</hi> and the <hi>Roman</hi> Doctrine <hi>of Praying to Angels:</hi> It ſeems at leaſt piouſly credible that thoſe who put on humane ſhapes to viſit <hi>Abraham,</hi> had Divinity about them, and repreſented no leſs than the Three Adorable Perſons of the Bleſſed <hi>Trinity</hi> (and therefore our Church reads this for the Firſt Leſſon upon <hi>Trinity Sunday.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In memory of this Glorious Apparition to <hi>Abraham,</hi> one of the Church-Hiſtorians gives <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bozomen.</hi> l. 2. c 4.</note> this account: That once every Year there was kept a <hi>Feſtival Day,</hi> where under the <hi>Doctor's Oak</hi> as they call'd it, where they ſuppos'd <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> ſate <hi>in the plains of Mamre,</hi> all Three Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions, <hi>Jews, Gentiles,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> had a <hi>Cuſtomary meeting,</hi> where they offer'd Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to their God according to the different
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55807:4"/> Rites and Ceremonies in uſe among them; untill the great Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any more of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> or <hi>Heatheniſh Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> to be kept there, Commanded the Place to be purg'd, and order'd a <hi>Chriſtian Temple</hi> to be erected, wherein only the followers of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> as the true <hi>Children of Abraham,</hi> ſhould be conven'd to Celebrate an <hi>Holy Anniverſary:</hi> Such a Solemnity as this which <hi>our Gracious King hath Licens'd us to obſerve</hi> in memory of our Fathers; who <hi>Commanded us their Children</hi> as <hi>Abraham</hi> did <hi>his, to keep the way of the Lord:</hi> And, in Charity to their Widows and Orphans, <hi>to do good and diſtribute unto them, for with ſuch Sacrifices God is pleas'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words may be eaſily obſerv'd theſe Four Parts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt here is eſtabliſht the Duty and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Parents to propagate true Religion to their Children, and the obligation of their Children to receive it from them: For the due exerciſe of that <hi>Paternal Power,</hi> and of this <hi>Filial obedience,</hi> is requir'd by Almighty God Reſpectively of both Parties, requir'd in the Perſons of <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Deſcendants, <hi>that he ſhould Command his Children and his</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:55807:5"/> 
               <hi>Houſhold after him to keep the way of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, here is a juſt and ſtrong preſumption, that eſpecially ſuch Fathers of Children as be alſo Fathers of the Church, will moſt effectually perform this important charge; and that the Children of ſuch <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Men, will alſo moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſly do their part, to obſerve the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections of their Parents and to follow their holy examples: This was a thing that God took for granted of Father <hi>Abraham,</hi> that he would take upon him <hi>to Teach as one having Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> and that his Godly Dictates would be admitted by all whom he owns for his Sons. <hi>I know that he will Command his Children,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, here is the full extent of that duty which lies upon Parents and this upon Children, thoſe to give and theſe to receive good Precepts, <hi>that they ſhould keep the way of the Lord:</hi> And then that <hi>way</hi> is made plain before them, it opens it ſelf into theſe two <hi>ways to do Juſtice and Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, here is the ample recompenſe of doing theſe duties with extraordinary ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication; it ſhall derive a Temporal and Eternal Bleſſing upon the heads of ſuch well-governing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55807:5"/> Parents, and ſuch well-Diſciplin'd Children; for theſe rewards are imply'd ſufficiently by that promiſe <hi>that the Lord may bring upon Abraham that which he hath ſpoken of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Here is eſtabliſh't the Duty and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Parents to propagate true Religion to their Children; and the Obligation of their Children to receive it from them: For the due exerciſe of that <hi>Paternal Power,</hi> and this <hi>Filial Obedience</hi> is requir'd by Almighty God reſpectively of both Parties, requir'd in the Perſons of <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Deſcendants, <hi>that he ſhould Command his Children and his Houſhold after him to keep the way of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That all Parents have a <hi>Commanding Power</hi> over their Children is ſo certain, that the firſt and ſureſt Foundation of <hi>Government</hi> was laid on <hi>Paternal Right.</hi> From God the great <hi>King of all the Earth,</hi> or from the Son of God, by whom <hi>he made the World,</hi> and by whom he governs it. From this Almighty King-maker, the firſt and greateſt Monarch was the firſt Man, whom the Apoſtle ſtyles <hi>the Son of God,</hi> and he was alſo the Father of all his Subjects.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55807:6"/> Whoever the ſecond was (and probably it was <hi>Methuſelah,</hi> who liv'd ſome Centuries in <hi>Adam's</hi> Lifetime, and dyed immediately before the <hi>Flood)</hi> the Third was <hi>Noah,</hi> he that began again the Government of a New World. Then <hi>Nimrod</hi> the firſt Tyrant lift up himſelf; and then we hear of <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> a King and Prieſt to whom <hi>Abraham</hi> paid his Tithes: And ſo we come to <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf: He was the chief and Head of the Holy Line, as I may call it; and what his Character was, appears from that Addreſs <hi>the Children of Heth</hi> made to <hi>Abraham, Hear us my Lord, thou art a Prince of God, or a mighty Prince among us.</hi> Now though I grant, that Univerſal Monarchy was gone long before this; though I do not deny, that before this time, the Diſperſion of Men, the Confuſion of Languages, and the neceſſity of other Accidents had introduc'd ſome other forms of Government, as <hi>Elective Monarchies, Ariſtocracies</hi> and perhaps <hi>Democracies</hi> (which Governments where they are Lawfully ſettled and Eſtabliſh't muſt <hi>for Conſcience-ſake</hi> be obey'd) yet if we believe this Book of <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> concerning the Original of humane Society, we cannot disbelieve this account that the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55807:6"/> Original of ſuch a Government as was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſupport that Society, was grounded upon Paternity; and that <hi>Abraham,</hi> as the Father of his Family, exercis'd this Dominion <hi>to Command his Children,</hi> not only thoſe Begotten of his own <hi>Body</hi> but thoſe alſo Born <hi>in his Houſe</hi> or within his <hi>Territories.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then ſince the World it ſelf was made by God with this great end and deſign that he might have a Church upon Earth; as St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells the Heathen <hi>Athenians,</hi> Acts 17. <hi>God hath made of one Blood all Nations of Men, to dwell on all the face of the Earth; and hath determin'd the times before appointed, and the Bounds of their Habitation, that they ſhould ſeek the Lord,</hi> That is ſeek how to Worſhip and ſerve him: What more effectual means could be us'd, or what more natural method than that the ſame perſons who brought us into the World ſhould be oblig'd to bring us into the Church? and to qualify them for this great work of Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, theſe two neceſſary things were provided for. Firſt God declar'd his Will how he would be Worſhipp'd and ſerv'd to our firſt Parents, and after them to the Patriarchs, <hi>to the intent</hi> (as the Patriarch <hi>David</hi> ſtates it) <hi>that</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:55807:7"/> 
               <hi>when they came up they might ſhew their Children the ſame.</hi> And as he gave our Fore-Fathers ſuch a <hi>Supernatural Revelation,</hi> as, if they would keep it ſafe, that would abundantly ſecure them from being <hi>Deceiv'd;</hi> ſo he gave <hi>all Parents</hi> ſuch a <hi>Natural</hi> intenſe <hi>affection</hi> towards their <hi>Children,</hi> as made it hard for Parents to be <hi>the Deceivers</hi> of their own <hi>Children,</hi> in the moſt important of all concerns, That, upon which depended no leſs than Eternity. Upon this account <hi>the Commonwealth of Plato</hi> (whoſe notions ſome would fain be reviving) could be no Soil for Religion to grow in: For his <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of Wives</hi> deſtroys the Principles of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>Natural Love</hi> to the Children of their own Bowels; a Principle upon which is founded the greateſt ſecurity (next to that of Gods promiſe to his Church) that Men will be faithful and careful in delivering to poſterity any thing of true Religion. But to come home to my Text, when God renew'd his Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> 'tis plain he truſted him as chief of a Choſen Family, with a Prophetick or Preaching, as well as Ruling Power: And the <hi>Prieſtly Office</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:55807:7"/> 
               <hi>as</hi> well as that of <hi>Governour,</hi> together with the <hi>double Portion,</hi> was to be continued and ſettled upon his <hi>Firſt Born;</hi> though upon the Tranſgreſſion of <hi>Reuben,</hi> the <hi>Governing part</hi> was transferr'd to <hi>Judah,</hi> the <hi>Prieſthood</hi> to <hi>Levi,</hi> and the <hi>Double Portion</hi> to <hi>Joſeph.</hi> And, which is very remarkable, the Sign of this <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> with <hi>Abraham,</hi> being <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> a painful and Bloody Ceremony (as the Wife of <hi>Moſes</hi> calls it;) yet from <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo many Hundred years, all the Numerous and almoſt innumerable Multitudes <hi>of the Children of Iſrael,</hi> were upon pain of Death, oblig'd to ſubmit to the Knife, and to embrace the Religion of their Fore-Fathers, without any Written <hi>Rule of Faith</hi> afforded them, that we know of; yet they were bound by vertue of <hi>Tradition</hi> from their Fathers, concerning the Doctrine and Miracles which God vouchſaf'd to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi> This <hi>Parents</hi> Tranſmitted to <hi>Children</hi> and the <hi>Chiefs</hi> or <hi>Elders of Iſrael</hi> (for ſuch we find there were when <hi>Moſes</hi> was firſt ſent to them) deliver'd to the lower or younger ſort of God's people.</p>
            <p>Yet I am far from aſſerting this <hi>Delivering</hi> of Religion from hand to hand downward
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55807:8"/> from <hi>Parents</hi> to <hi>Children</hi> to be <hi>always</hi> the <hi>only</hi> means, or at any time the <hi>Infallible</hi> means, <hi>to keep the Faith whole and undefiled.</hi> I am well aware that from one ſinful Generation to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Parents</hi> and <hi>Children</hi> have ſo fail'd, they in delivering, and theſe in receiving that which God revealed of himſelf and his Divine Will, that Idolatry was all the Religion moſt Men had left them. I only alledge this to be ever indiſpenſably the Duty, but I do not pretend it was conſtantly the Practice of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo neerly Related to one another. And the ſtiffeſt defenders of <hi>the Oral-Tradition way</hi> in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> may be as eaſily refuted as were thoſe <hi>Sceptic Philoſophers</hi> that denied <hi>Motion,</hi> but had nothing to ſay when the <hi>Cynic</hi> roſe up and <hi>walkt:</hi> ſo they who main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it to be impoſſible, that ever their Faith ſhould have chang'd, need only be ſhew'd how much they themſelves have alter'd it; how <hi>they have ſought out many Inventions,</hi> and this for <hi>one;</hi> as if their <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Mothers</hi> (adding to them, if they pleaſe, their <hi>Nurſes</hi> too) were the only <hi>Guardians</hi> even of the Chriſtian Religion, and <hi>Truſtees</hi> for the <hi>Depoſitum</hi> of the <hi>Faith;</hi> as if neither <hi>the Scriptures were able to</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:55807:8"/> 
               <hi>make us wiſe unto Salvation,</hi> nor the Church Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative, or the <hi>Prieſts Lips could preſerve Knowledge,</hi> ſaving Knowledge, nor propagate it ſo infallibly, as the familiar Colloquies of thoſe who have ſo often turn'd it into <hi>Old Wives Fables.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if the <hi>Fathers of our Fleſh</hi> (as the Apoſtle calls them) are not to be altogether relyed upon; yet to go on to my Second part, 'tis to be hop'd ſuch Fathers as be alſo <hi>Spiritual Fathers,</hi> will never fail in this duty of <hi>Commanding their Children to keep the way of the Lord.</hi> And that ſuch Inſtructors and Directors <hi>of the Tribe of Levi</hi> ſhall never fail in the Church, that Gracious Promiſe or Prophecy is our abundant Security, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, the Prieſts and Levites ſhall not want a Man before me.</hi> Jer. 33. 18. parallel to that in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> cap. 30. ver. 20. <hi>Thy Teachers ſhall not be remov'd into Corners any more, but thine eye ſhall ſee thy Teachers,</hi> and farther explain'd by that Glorious Aſſurance to the Chriſtian Church, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> c. 59. <hi>v. ult. This is my Covenant with them ſaith the Lord, my Spirit that is upon thee and my words that I have put in thy Mouth, ſhall not depart out of thy Mouth, nor out of the Mouth of thy Seed, nor out of the Mouth of thy Seeds Seed, ſaith the</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:55807:9"/> 
               <hi>Lord, from henceforth and for ever.</hi> The Sum of all which promiſes amounts to this, that the Church ſhall never be left without true and good Paſtors, the ſuppoſition of that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the very Definition of a form'd Church, <hi>Grex Paſtori adunatus;</hi> the <hi>Sheep</hi> ſhall never be depriv'd of a <hi>viſible ſufficient</hi> number of Faithful <hi>Shepherds,</hi> who ſhall make appear their Love to the great Shepherd of the Sheep, <hi>the Biſhop of our Souls,</hi> by feeding his whole Flock; the ſmall as well as the great, the younger and weaker as well as the older and ſtronger; for in the charge that Chriſt gave to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> a particular tender care is taken <hi>of the Lambs;</hi> eſpecially for the uſe of theſe <hi>the little Children,</hi> as the Apoſtles call them, or <hi>the Men of little Faith,</hi> as Chriſt was pleas'd to call the Apoſtles themſelves in their Novitiate or State of Pupillage; for ſuch as theſe, I ſay, was deſign'd <hi>the form of ſound words,</hi> as one Scripture calls it, or <hi>the form of Doctrine</hi> as in another place. If it be demanded what ſuch a <hi>Form</hi> was; I anſwer, it was either the very ſame that we call <hi>the Apoſtles Creed,</hi> or at leaſt ſome <hi>Apoſtolick Creed,</hi> ſome Compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous account of <hi>the Catholick Faith.</hi> And <hi>Iſaac,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:55807:9"/> 
               <hi>the their of Promiſe,</hi> ſo long ago, was a kind of <hi>Catechumen,</hi> and the firſt of thoſe meant in my Text. He was to be taught the ſum of the <hi>Law</hi> deliver'd to <hi>Abraham</hi> in theſe few words, <hi>Walk before me and be thou perfect;</hi> and he was to learn the ſum of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> from him that was alſo Taught it of God in this ſhort Creed, and <hi>in thy Seed ſhall all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Earth be Bleſſed.</hi> Men, Women, and Children are included in that Univerſal Grace; and if very Children of all Nations have any ſhare in this <hi>Promiſe,</hi> then are they alſo within that <hi>Precept</hi> given by Chriſt to his Apoſtles, <hi>go Teach and Baptize all Nations:</hi> Not that of neceſſity they are to be inſtructed firſt and Chriſten'd afterwards; but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, <hi>make Diſciples of them,</hi> apply and enter them forthwith into the School of Chriſt; as <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> upon the Birth of his Son <hi>Alexander</hi> preſently ſaid to <hi>Ariſtotle, There's your Scholar;</hi> as if he had ſaid, <hi>I Conſtitute you his Tutor,</hi> from henceforth ſee him well order'd and inſtructed as he grows more and more capable of Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And if <hi>Levit.</hi> 25. Children are ſtyl'd by Almighty God, <hi>my Servants;</hi> then why not as well <hi>my Diſciples?</hi> by parity of reaſon this
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55807:10"/> Religious Care of Inſtruction extends it ſelf to thoſe that are <hi>Children in underſtanding,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſtiles them. For as <hi>there is a Child,</hi> ſay's the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, of a Hundred years old,</hi> that is, for the ripeneſs of his knowledge; ſo it follows there, <hi>the Sinner of a Hundred years old ſhall be accurſed.</hi> And to deliver ſuch from the Curſe upon thoſe that do <hi>err from Gods Commandments,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks, to make them capable of <hi>the Bleſſing</hi> upon the true Genuine Children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> faithful good Chriſtians; as this is the peculiar buſineſs <hi>of the Tribe of Levi,</hi> to <hi>do good unto all Men,</hi> ſo eſpecially to thoſe who may be ſtiled more <hi>peculiarly the houſhold of Faith,</hi> for being <hi>of the houſe of Levi.</hi> For if St. <hi>Paul</hi> has ſtated it <hi>to his own Son,</hi> and Scholar <hi>Timothy,</hi> that <hi>if any provide not for his own,</hi> and <hi>eſpecially for thoſe of his own houſe,</hi> (where it means providing maintenance for their Bodily ſuſtenance) <hi>he hath denied the Faith,</hi> and <hi>is worſe than an Infidel;</hi> Then a <hi>Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> is worſt of all, that provides not well for the Souls of thoſe deſcended from his own Loyns: And if every <hi>Maſter of a Family</hi> be in ſome ſenſe <hi>a Biſhop in his own Houſe;</hi> then the <hi>Elders</hi> or Governours in the Church, if
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55807:10"/> they would be counted <hi>worthy of the double Honour for Ruling well,</hi> muſt own a double obligation <hi>to Build up ſuch in the moſt Holy Faith,</hi> to <hi>breed them up in the Nurture and admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Duties of <hi>Teaching</hi> and <hi>Learning,</hi> being thus ſecur'd, next I proceed to ſettle the ſubject matter of ſuch <hi>Divine Lectures;</hi> and ſo I am fallen upon my Third Part, the full extent of theſe Inſtitutions, <hi>that they ſhould keep the way of the Lord to do juſtice and judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what is it firſt, <hi>to keep the way of the Lord?</hi> I anſwer in the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>to hold the Myſtery of the Faith in a pure Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſome tender ears it ſounds but harſhly in the Creed we call the <hi>Athanaſian,</hi> and it ſeems <hi>a hard ſaying, which Faith except every one doe keep whole and undefil'd, without doubt he ſhall periſh everlaſtingly;</hi> and then again, <hi>This is the Catholick Faith which except a Man believe faithfully be cannot be ſav'd.</hi> But this <hi>keeping the Faith</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes it firſt committed to any ones <hi>Cuſtody;</hi> or, in the words of my Text, <hi>this keeping the way of the Lord</hi> ſuppoſes the ſufficient knowledg of it to be firſt imparted; and ſo <hi>Believing faithfully</hi> preſuppoſes a <hi>Diſcovery</hi> and <hi>Delivery;</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:55807:11"/> and therefore the <hi>Faith for which we are bound to contend earneſtly,</hi> the Eſſential or <hi>neceſſary Faith,</hi> is juſtly call'd <hi>the Faith once deliver'd to the Saints.</hi> Wherever the Goſpel is Preach'd, there of neceſſity <hi>muſt this Faith be deliver'd:</hi> So that in this ſenſe we call it <hi>Neceſſary Faith,</hi> meaning that Doctrine which all Chriſtian Paſtors are oblig'd to <hi>Preach,</hi> and <hi>wo unto them if they Preach not that Goſpel,</hi> or if they do <hi>Preach</hi> any other; That Doctrine which all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that hear it <hi>Preach'd</hi> by theſe Paſtors are oblig'd to <hi>admit; That way of the Lord</hi> which all Men are conſtantly <hi>to keep,</hi> when once they are ſhew'd it; and <hi>Commanded to walk in it.</hi> But this is none of their caſe of whom it may be truly ſaid, <hi>How ſhould they believe in him of whom they have not heard, and how ſhould they hear without a Preacher?</hi> What parts of Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation are ſo abſolutely neceſſary, as none ſhall be ſav'd without both <hi>Hearing</hi> of them and <hi>Believing</hi> them; what is ſo fundamental, is among the <hi>Arcana Imperii, the ſecrets of God's Kingdom; levius eſt neſcîſſe quam Errâſſe; 'tis a leſs guilt</hi> (ſays St. <hi>Auguſtine) to be ignorant of the Truth, than to maintain a falſe Doctrine.</hi> Suppoſe that any of <hi>thoſe Diſciples</hi> that St. <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:55807:11"/> found at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> thoſe <hi>Diſciples</hi> (for ſo they are ſtyled for all their ignorance) that <hi>had not ſo much as heard whether there were any Holy Ghoſt:</hi> Suppoſe I ſay, that any of them had dyed in that State of <hi>Ignorance,</hi> and that <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> had been <hi>Invincible,</hi> or though a little <hi>Culpable,</hi> yet not <hi>Criminal,</hi> to whom <hi>little</hi> of knowledge <hi>was given, of them would little have been requir'd.</hi> The Church is far enough off from <hi>Damning ſuch</hi> for not <hi>keeping that Faith</hi> of which no means was afforded to poſſeſs them. And ſince <hi>Life and Immortality are ſaid to be brought to Light in the Goſpel;</hi> which muſt ſuppoſe, that before, and under the Law, the Fathers were much in the dark concerning the World to come. Since 'tis the Character of the Chriſtian Faith to conſiſt of <hi>Reveal'd Myſteries that were hid from the beginning of the World;</hi> 'tis needleſs for us to ſet the bounds and limits of that <hi>neceſſary Faith</hi> which <hi>Abraham</hi> was oblig'd to Preach and <hi>his Children</hi> to hear. How explicit a belief of <hi>the Holy Trinity;</hi> How cleer a Notion <hi>of the Reſurrection of the Body;</hi> What kind of <hi>Meſſiah</hi> was expected by the <hi>Commonwealth of Iſrael</hi> in thoſe early days; is neither <hi>neceſſary,</hi> nor perhaps very <hi>poſſible</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:55807:12"/> for us at this diſtance to determine. 'Tis enough that God had ſhew'd them a way to Heaven by embracing ſuch a <hi>Faith</hi> as well as by <hi>doing ſuch works:</hi> And the <hi>Spiritual Guides</hi> in all Ages had the Office of crying after God's Faithful people, <hi>This is the way, walk in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for the Practical parts of Piety which <hi>Abraham was to Command his Children, to do Juſtice and Judgment;</hi> (where <hi>Juſtice</hi> ſignifies <hi>Beneficence</hi> or <hi>Mercy</hi> being joyn'd with <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and <hi>Judgment</hi> denotes <hi>Integrity</hi> without any fraud or deceit) theſe were <hi>Innate</hi> Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, or parts of <hi>Natural Religion</hi> (as we call it) now it is truly ſaid, <hi>Naturalia Supponuntur in eſſe;</hi> whatever is Natural to Mankind is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to be in all Men: But yet theſe qualities will prove but <hi>half Vertues</hi> in the beſt <hi>Natures</hi> without ſome <hi>Gracious Education</hi> and <hi>Exerciſe;</hi> 'tis certain they will riſe higher, and be more Heroic in thoſe who ſtand in the clearer Lights; to ſee the brighter Idea's of theſe Graces, and to view them in all their Glories. There is difference too in the obligations and juſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations upon ſeveral orders and degrees of Men in the Church. But <hi>the Sons of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> as better <hi>taught</hi> than others, ought to be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55807:12"/> 
               <hi>Leaders</hi> of others, if not <hi>Teachers,</hi> nay <hi>Teachers</hi> in the beſt way of Inſtructing, by the uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troulable Authority of <hi>Exemplary</hi> Living. But ſince <hi>to do Juſtice and Judgment,</hi> does, in few words, include the whole Duty of Man, which ſtretches out its Branches ſo far; I ſhall extend my diſcourſe but to theſe Two parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, which ought to be the proper vertues, the ſpecial Characters, and as it were <hi>the Badges</hi> of all in this <hi>Corporation.</hi> Thoſe two Particulars are.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, Principles of Loyalty to the King and of Love to our Country.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, of Love to the Church, and of Charity to this Eccleſiaſtical Corporation. If other Vertues be with long practice ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd; theſe two ſhould be as it were born and bred with us.</p>
            <p>And firſt we are in a ſpecial manner obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to be eminently Loyal to our Prince, and to be trueſt Lovers of our Country. Of the former of theſe vertues <hi>Abraham</hi> could be no example, becauſe he was no ſubject. His province was to Command and not to obey. For as <hi>the Children of Heth</hi> entitle him <hi>a Prince;</hi> ſo the Son of <hi>Syrach</hi> goes yet farther, <hi>Abraham</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:55807:13"/> 
               <hi>was a Great Father of many Nations, in Glory was there none like unto him.</hi> Yet he left the Doctrine of Obedience, not only that obedience due to God, but that alſo due to himſelf, being a <hi>Prince</hi> as well as a <hi>Parent,</hi> eſtabliſh'd by one of the nobleſt inſtances that ever was ſince the World began, except that great Exemplar of which the ſtory of his offering up <hi>Iſaac</hi> was a <hi>figure:</hi> He taught his Son, being then young and vigorous, able to bear the wood of the Burnt Offering, to ſubmit his neck to the Burden: Then, to ſuffer his Aged Father who had power of Life and Death over him, to <hi>bind</hi> him, and <hi>lay him on the Altar upon the wood,</hi> to take the coming blow with open eyes, and all this without making any reſiſtance. And then for Love to his Country, that which God had ſettled upon his Poſterity, ſee how his care and concern extended as far as even to <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> which being Adjacent parts of that promis'd Inheritance, God Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcends, as it were, to ask his conſent and permiſſion, before he would execute vengeance upon them: <hi>And the Lord ſaid, ſhall I hide from Abraham that thing which I do?</hi> But on the other ſide, how does <hi>Abraham</hi> Wreſtle with God
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55807:13"/> 
               <hi>to pluck them as Brands out of the Fire?</hi> With what humble ſubmiſſion, and yet with what magnanimity does he gain his ground by ſteps, to bring his wicked and wretched neighbours within the reach of Omnipotent mercy? had there <hi>been only Ten Righteous among them,</hi> It might have been ſaid of this great and good Patriot <hi>Abraham,</hi> as God himſelf was pleas'd to ſay of the Grandſon <hi>Jacob, as a Prince haſt thou Power with God and Men, and haſt prevail'd.</hi> And theſe ſhould be our Hereditary Qualities, Loyalty, and Love of our Country. Sedition and Faction are <hi>ungodly</hi> in any of the Sons of Men, but <hi>unnatural</hi> in a <hi>Clergyman's-Son.</hi> He ſhould ſtart at the very thought of being an <hi>Incendiary,</hi> while he has the Character of his <hi>Father</hi> in any Reverence: As <hi>Cicero</hi> when he produc'd in the Senate an Intercepted Letter from <hi>Lentulus</hi> to the Arch-Traytor <hi>Catiline,</hi> upon reviewing the Seal, and perceiving upon it the venerable Image of the <hi>Grandfather</hi> to <hi>Lentulus,</hi> an excellent good Old Patriot, the <hi>Conſul</hi> ſeems to wonder the very ſight of that face ſhould not have recall'd and reclaim'd him from his baſe and cruel purpoſes, to prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Honour and Kindneſs to his Native
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55807:14"/> City. But to be <hi>Abhorrers of ſuch Aſſociations</hi> as our late <hi>Catilines</hi> made, is too little for Men ſo Born and ſo bred up, ſo well Inſtructed and Catechis'd as we are ſuppos'd to have been; 'Tis not enough for us to yield only <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> in ſuch times of <hi>Exigence;</hi> We ſhould be as forward as the formoſt to pay a vigorous <hi>Active Obedience</hi> eſpecially to <hi>ſuch a Prince</hi> as has done us the great Grace to make himſelf our <hi>Founder.</hi> For as it muſt be confeſs'd that never any Royal Family has better deſerv'd the Title of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Benefactors to the Church,</hi> which none of them ever diminiſh'd in the leaſt <hi>Priviledge,</hi> but have all of them nobly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd and greatly enlarg'd her <hi>Charters;</hi> ſo it muſt be thankfully acknowledg'd that towards <hi>us his Majeſty</hi> has exceeded the Bounty of all his Glorious Progenitors. He has taken away our reproach, for the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had made us a <hi>Proverb,</hi> as if <hi>the Son of a Prieſt</hi> were no better than <hi>Filius Populi, a Son of the People:</hi> But the King does ſufficiently own us to have been <hi>Legitimate;</hi> and has in a manner undertaken to be himſelf our <hi>Guardian</hi> And with great ſenſe of Gratitude, you did but this time Twelvemonth at our ſolemn
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55807:14"/> meeting, Vote an <hi>Addreſs</hi> worthy of your ſelves, wherein you have plighted your Faith to <hi>Aſſert the Rights of this Hereditary Imperial Crown,</hi> and this you did with the lowdeſt and joyfulleſt <hi>Acclamations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as we are moſt particularly and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſibly oblig'd to be zealouſly true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to our Prince and Country; ſo in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place, we of all Mankind are moſt ſtrictly engag'd to be moſt unfeignedly and concernedly <hi>Friends to the Church.</hi> This was a Temper of mind which <hi>Abraham</hi> effectually <hi>Commanded</hi> and <hi>Taught his Children,</hi> when he diſcarded and expos'd one of them, that was <hi>Iſmael,</hi> for but making a <hi>mock of Iſaac,</hi> whom the Apoſtle makes a Type of the Church; and repreſents that whole Tranſaction for a <hi>figure</hi> of ſuch <hi>as are Born after the fleſh,</hi> how they <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute ſuch as are Born after the ſpirit.</hi> For <hi>a Mans foes to be thoſe of his own houſhold</hi> is hard indeed: But that any of the Churches enemies ſhould be ſome of thoſe who came out of her own Bowels, is a great deal harder. If there be any ſuch, they are moſt properly call'd <hi>a Generation of Vipers.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:55807:15"/>
            <p> But whatever he be in his Name, he is in his Nature an <hi>Iſmael,</hi> a kind of <hi>Wild Man,</hi> who can put off the <hi>moſt Natural</hi> affection that the Son of a <hi>Clergy-man</hi> ows to the <hi>Church;</hi> which is ſomething more than his ſpiritual Mother, and to whoſe tender care he belong'd, as ſoon as ever he came into <hi>the world.</hi> To call ſuch a one a <hi>Janizary</hi> may be thought too much; and yet, conſidering ſome aggravating Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, 'tis indeed too little; for thoſe Children of Chriſtian Parents are ſnatch'd from the breaſts of their Mothers ſoon after they are Dedicated to God in the Bleſſed Laver of Regeneration, the wretched Infants, are worſe than offer'd to <hi>Moloch</hi> who kill'd them preſently; they are Conſecrated to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet,</hi> they are Educated in all the prejudices of Mahumetaniſm; which makes their Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to Chriſtianity <hi>much</hi> their <hi>misfortune,</hi> though <hi>very much</hi> alſo their <hi>fault.</hi> But what excuſe can be made to alleviate the guilt of one, brought up, not at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel</hi> as <hi>Saul</hi> was, but like <hi>Timothy</hi> bred up as it were by St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, or by ſuch as <hi>were followers of him as he was of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:55807:15"/>
            <p> But on the other ſide, what a vaſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage may the Church derive from the kindneſs of ſo many Worthy and Excellent perſons as make up this Solemn Aſſembly, who though very conſiderable in themſelves, yet are few in number compar'd with the reſt of our Brethren (as I take leave to ſtile them) diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers'd over theſe Three Kingdoms: Many whom God has bleſs'd, and who may prove a Bleſſing to very many. For though <hi>Jacob curs'd</hi> the wrath of <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi;</hi> yet it was alſo part of his <hi>Bleſſing</hi> upon them, and through them upon all the reſt of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Children, <hi>that he would divide the Tribe of Levi in Jacob, and ſcatter them in Iſrael;</hi> that ſo they might carry along with them his Benedictions, that they might diſpenſe them far and near, that they might be themſelves a common Bleſſing. So at this time are the <hi>Sons of the Sons of Levi</hi> in their ſeveral ſtations: So many wealthy Citizens, ſuch as the <hi>Book of Wiſdom</hi> deſcribes in that Chapter where we find the praiſes of <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Children, <hi>Men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown'd for their power, giving Counſel by their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,</hi> that is <hi>Men of buſineſs,</hi> excellent managers to make up <hi>your Court of Aſſiſtants,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:55807:16"/> So many honourable Gentlemen and Noble Knights rais'd by their merits and ſervices at Sea and Land, bound by their Order as well as by their Extraction, to protect your Widows and Orphans: So many <hi>Clergy-men</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to do their parts, and to make good that Plea for the <hi>Marry'd Clergy,</hi> that a great part of the <hi>Clergy</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and among them ſome of the beſt of the <hi>Clergy</hi> are the Sons of the <hi>Married Clergy.</hi> Such a <hi>Corporation</hi> as this will bear up the Character given by the Apoſtle to the <hi>Church</hi> it ſelf, as that is a <hi>Corporation,</hi> depending, as do all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Societies, and this for one, upon <hi>Chriſt the Head, from whom the whole Body fitly joyn'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and compacted by that which every joynt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth, according to the effectual working in the meaſure of every part, maketh increaſe of the Body.</hi> But this falls in with my fourth and laſt head of diſcourſe (of which very briefly) the <hi>Bleſſings</hi> upon well-governing Parents, and well-diſciplin'd Children, <hi>that the Lord may bring upon Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, that which he hath ſpoken of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what is that? all Earthly and Heavenly, all bodily and ſpiritual, all temporal and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal good things upon <hi>Him</hi> and <hi>His;</hi> eſpecially
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55807:16"/> 
               <hi>His by Adoption, His</hi> by <hi>Faith,</hi> any that follow <hi>His,</hi> and <hi>their</hi> Footſteps; <hi>His</hi> in Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Devotion, <hi>theirs</hi> in Learning it: All theſe ſhall be thus <hi>Bleſſed with Faithful Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if thus ſhall <hi>his Seed be Bleſs'd</hi> with <hi>both</hi> hands, with the Bleſſing of the <hi>Left</hi> as well as the <hi>Right</hi> hand; how comes it to paſs that ſo many of their miſerable <hi>Orphans</hi> call for our help and Relief? How are Times chang'd ſince <hi>David</hi> made it his Obſervation, <hi>I have been young and now am old, yet ſaw I never the Righteous forſaken, nor his Seed begging their Bread?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I anſwer, neither does <hi>David</hi> here ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that it can never happen thus, but that it falls out rarely, <hi>He never ſaw it.</hi> He never <hi>ſaw the Righteous forſaken, nor his Seed begging their Bread,</hi> that is, he <hi>never ſaw them begging</hi> and quite <hi>forſaken,</hi> which muſt be repeated: That <hi>the Children of the Righteous</hi> ſhould <hi>never beg their Bread,</hi> was no where promiſed the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves: They were not exempted from this as a Temporary <hi>evil,</hi> either for <hi>Tryal</hi> or for <hi>Puniſhment.</hi> They were not priviledg'd from being beſeig'd in their Cities, not yet from being driven out of their Native
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55807:17"/> Country; and <hi>David</hi> himſelf in the time of his Flight and Baniſhment was reduc'd to that extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, as to ask and receive <hi>the Shew-Bread</hi> to keep himſelf and his followers from ſtarving: But that <hi>there ſhould be none to pity or have Compaſſion upon the Fatherleſs Children or Widow;</hi> that was the <hi>Curſe</hi> on <hi>Judas;</hi> and <hi>David</hi> had never ſeen that heavy Curſe fall on any Children of <hi>Abraham.</hi> 'Tis only upon ſuch <hi>Apoſtates</hi> from the Faith, ſuch as <hi>Sin Trecherouſly,</hi> the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt lays ſuch load, <hi>Let the Runegates continue in ſcarceneſs.</hi> I anſwer ſecondly, thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of plenty and <hi>eating the Fat of the Land,</hi> muſt either be abated to us, or elſe ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz'd to an Evangelical ſenſe; they were more literaly fullfil'd to that Carnal people the <hi>Jews,</hi> than muſt be expected by us <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> our part is to be always diſpos'd for Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom; and God has never engag'd to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand <hi>that theſe Stones ſhall be made Bread,</hi> rather than any Son or Daughter of <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhall be ſtarv'd into Heaven; no more than he has oblig'd himſelf, <hi>out of theſe Stones to raiſe up Children unto Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for the <hi>better</hi> promiſes, <hi>Thoſe exceeding great and pretious Promiſes,</hi> as the Apoſtle calls
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55807:17"/> them, <hi>In thy Seed ſhall all the Families of the Earth be Bleſs'd;</hi> the <hi>multiplying</hi> of <hi>Abraham's Children like the Sand of the Sea, or the Stars of Heaven.</hi> Theſe <hi>Benedictions</hi> are in a manner appropriated to us <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> preſſes the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> hard with theſe Glorious Prophecies, concerning the vaſt number of thoſe that <hi>ſhould flock into the Church,</hi> that its Sons ſhould be innumerable; whereas they of that <hi>Sect,</hi> or indeed of any other, were a handfull of Men in compariſon, how vainly ſoever they pretended to be the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> upon which thoſe unſpeakable <hi>Bleſſings</hi> are entail'd and ſettled <hi>to the end of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Enough, I hope, has been ſaid of the great rewards in this World, and in that to come; for the <hi>Righteous,</hi> and thoſe that <hi>Teach their Children Righteouſneſs,</hi> to reinforce this obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon us, eſpecially upon us the Children of ſuch <hi>Fathers</hi> as were alſo our <hi>Ghoſtly Fathers.</hi> To call to mind the wiſe dictates, to revolve the memorable ſayings, and to recollect the worthy Acts of ſuch venerable <hi>Guides,</hi> is one of the beſt <hi>Syſtems</hi> of <hi>Practical Divinity</hi> for our uſe. For if St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> himſelf, the Night after his Mothers Funeral, could not help falling into
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55807:18"/> moſt tender Paſſions, upon the remembrance of <hi>Monica</hi> his devout Mother, how many weariſome ſteps ſhe had taken to follow his idle Progreſſes in his vitious youth, that ſhe might recover <hi>her loſt ſheep,</hi> and bring <hi>him home to Chriſt's Flock;</hi> then what mighty powerfull effects will it work upon any one of us that had a pious <hi>Churchman</hi> to his <hi>Father,</hi> to reflect on his admonitions, ſuch as for their Gravity and Piety might have become the mouth of St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> himſelf? Such <hi>a Reverend Spiritual Father,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Saint</hi> has this whole Society loſt in our late <hi>moſt worthy Preſident.</hi> For how can I treat of this ſubject of teaching others <hi>to keep the way of the Lord,</hi> and treat of it before this Audience, without one word in <hi>Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of that incomparable perſon, who with almoſt an incredible concurrence of Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities both of mind and body, and with a moſt indefatigable induſtry; yet with all this was not more fitted to <hi>acquire</hi> all parts of <hi>Divine Learning,</hi> than he was <hi>apt to Teach:</hi> And <hi>being Dead he yet ſpeaks,</hi> and Teaches us by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; he perſwades as powerfully as if <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> himſelf had <hi>Commanded us</hi> as his <hi>Children;</hi> he Preaches more efficaciouſly, than if <hi>Abraham</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:55807:18"/> ſhould ſend us a <hi>Lazarus from the Dead,</hi> to preſs Repentance and Holy Living. He exhorts us <hi>not to be weary</hi> (as he never was) <hi>of well doing,</hi> he charges us <hi>to be</hi> (as he was) <hi>Stedfaſt, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable, always abounding in the work of the Lord, knowing that our labour is not in vain in the Lord,</hi> To whom, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
